## Slim Ouertani June-81, Tunisian

- ouertani@gmail.com 00966583012381 Riyadh (Saudi Arabia)
- linkedin.com/in/ouertani ouertani.github.io infoq.com/profile/Slim-Ouertani/ twitter.com/ouertani

## CTO - CIO

## **Summary**

Fr editor, Big Data Science, Cloud and SOA Certified trainer, founder and organizer of Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup. After his engineer's degree in computer science, Slim spent over than 16 years in multinational companies such as Orange, Sagem, and GE as architect, international agile coach and Head of IT development department. His main role was to build, design and collaborate in the development of enterprise solutions.

Slim regularly contributes to InfoQ-FR commuyou to follow him on twitter @ouertani.

Slim Ouertani is enterprise architect, InfoQ- nity where he is the author of many articles and news. He's broad certified as in addition to his SOA, Cloud and Big Data Science certifications: Trainer, Architect & Engineer, Slim holds multiple certifications including Togaf 9, Archimate 2, IT4IT, SABSA, PMP, ITIL, CMMi, Mongo, Spring, JAVA, SCALA and reactive programming...

Slim enjoys open source contribution and invite

## Experience

Nomd

CTO

RIYADH, SAUDI ARABIA 04-2020 - present

- Setting a vision for how technology will be used in the group.
- Ensuring that the technological resources meet the company's short and long-term needs.
- Outline the goals for research and development.
- Creating timelines for the development and deployment of all technological services.
- Making executive decisions on behalf of the company's technological requirements.
- Ensuring all technology practices adhere to regulatory standards.
- Managing technology budgets and time frames.

**GE** Digital

Riyadh, SAUDI ARABIA 06-2019 - 03-2020

#### **Senior Architect**

- Drive growth, improve efficiency and customer satisfaction in the health care digital transformation
- Direct and manage different consultation technology companies for digital transformation project (100+ million usd)
- Architecture lead for Mawid V2 Service
- Ensuring that IT contracts and service levels are negotiated in line with all strategic aims and financial constraints.

machinestalk

RIYADH, SAUDI ARABIA

03-2017 - 05-2019

**CTO** 

- Key contributor in the company transformation to be top ranked IoT service provider kingdom wide
- Create and direct a development center in Tunisia (35 engineers + Administrative staff)
- Set a strategy and direction for the technology and IT departments
- Created development, quality assurance, and implementation methodologies, processes and teams to support demanding customer base and highly aggressive business goals.
- Teams restructure making sure the staff have clear areas of responsibility and lines of ownership
- Responsible of the technology strategy implementation
- Responsible of building and implementing the new IoT framework.
- Supervise system infrastructure to ensure functionality and efficiency
- Build quality assurance and data protection processes.

#### Al-Elm Information Security

RIYADH, SAUDI ARABIA

06-2014 - 03-2016

#### **Solution Architect**

- Member/Founder of ELM Development Architecture Center of Excellence.
- EPG committee member, responsible of the architecture models, oversee the process architecture, approve it and ensuring the process improvement.

- Architecting and Designing enterprise solutions using diverse technology stack
- Work with peers to conduct Solution Architecture Reviews for a broad set of projects
- Review and provide input into functional & non-functional requirements
- Provide consulting and conduct reviews through the development lifecycle
- Defining the Architecture and guiding the use of various tools, technologies and techniques in the realization of that Architecture:
  - HIS system architecture, SDP, WASL,...
  - EA Riyadah, API GWT, Microservices...
- Create and maintain a set of standard practices, patterns and anti-patterns and ensure the appropriate usage of that.

#### Sofrecom (Orange FT Group)

Tunis, Tunisia 03-2013 - 06-2014

#### Software Architect, International Agile Coach

Manage and direct virtual distributed teams

Make or Buy Analysis

- Establish regular meetings to review technical designs and provide mentoring and guidance
- Mentor development teams on different architecture and design paradigms or practices
- Maintain a knowledge base of emerging technologies and products
- Scrum Master, Enterprise Architect

Zenika Paris, FRANCE

**JEE Architect** 

Client: Bouygues Telecom

Project: Home Automation (2 months)

BBox embedded automation solution communicating with centralized system

• Client: SwissPost

Project: Image Plus (2 months)

• Online outsourcing solution for picture processing.

Tunis, Tunisia

#### **Head of Development and Tools Manager**

01-2010 - 11-2012

12-2012 - 03-2013

• Architecture, development and implementation of a web service platform:

IN/AIR, BSCS/CMS/Data Charging/CRM/IVR/USSD
 Development of the "after sales service" solution

• Launch of BI departement

• Different applications: inter systems and synchronization platforms, web application...

#### Sagem Software & Technologies

Tunis, Tunisia 06-2009 - 01-2010

**Solution Architect** 

 Architecture design and integration of a communication server and administration of remote gateways.

**Solution Architect** 03-2008 - 06-2009

- Modular OSGi Server architecture under Linux platform responsible for controlling and interacting with electricity counters in order to retrieve statistics and have data storing/manipulation via different technologies and frameworks
  - DISTRIBUTED COMPUTING, Cryptography

#### Solution Architect & Team Leader

12-2007 - 03-2008

Designing an SOA architecture and implementation of an Intranet service for human resources.

**STMicroelectronics** Coordinator

Tunis, Tunisia 02-2006 - 12-2007

Implementing Intranet tools used for monitoring the evolution of validation campaigns.

Developer 12-2005 - 02-2006

• Validating processors and compilers under different platforms.

# **GL TRADE**

Tunis, Tunisia

Developer & designer 08-2005 - 12-2005

• GL TACTICS: A trader module enhancing the efficiency of the negotiating teams giving them the possibility to customize the implementation strategies and accelerate the decision process.

Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of work experiences along with recommendations.

### Certificate

IT4IT, Open Group SABSA Charted Architect, SABSA

Big Data Science Trainer, Arcitura	09-2016	
Big Data Science Engineer, Arcitura	With Honors, 08-2016	
Big Data Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 05-2016	
Archimate Certified, Open Group	Score 82%, 02-2016	
Archimate Foundation, Open Group	Score 97%, 02-2016	
Cloud Trainer, Arcitura	10-2015	
Cloud Architect, Arcitura	With Honors, 10-2015	
Cloud Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 09-2015	
Togaf Certified, Open Group	Score 90%, 06-2015	
ITIL Foundation, Exin	Score 95%, 06-2015	
Togaf Foundation, Open Group	Score 95%, 04-2015	
Project Management Professional, PMI	03-2015	
SOA Trainer, Arcitura	01-2015	
SOA Architect, Arcitura	With Honors, 12-2014	
SOA Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 11-2014	
Introduction to Cmmi for development, Cmmi Institute	09-2014	
Entrepreneurship for all, EFFECTUATION, EMLYON	Score 75,8%, 01-2014	
Principles of Reactive Programming, Coursera	Score 97.5%, 01-2014	
MongoDB for DBAs, MongoDB	Score 94%, 11-2013	
MongoDb for java, MongoDb	Score 95%, 10-2013	
Spring Framework 3, Pivotal	Score 94%, 02-2013	
Java 6 Programmer Certified Professional, Oracle	Score 100%, 08-2012	
Team Performance, STMicroelectronics	04-2007	
English, British Council	4B, 02-2007	
GL Certified Professional, GL TRADE	09-2005	

## **Education**

National School of Computer ScienceENSI  Graduation Project in Computer Engineering	Tunis,Tunisia 2005
National School of Computer Science ENSI  Engineer Degree in Computer Science	Tunis, Tunisia 2002 – 2005
Tunis Preparatory Institute for Engineering StudiesIPEIT	Tunis, Tunisia
Preparatory Courses (Math Sup, Math Spe)	2000 – 2002
Hannibal	Ariana, Tunisia
(Pre-university Secondary Education)	1994 – 2000

## **Other Activities**

#### InfoQ Fr Editor

http://www.infoq.com/fr/author/Slim-Ouertani

## Founder & Organizer

Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup

http://www.meetup.com/Riyadh-IT-Architecture

#### **BLOGGGING**

http://java.dzone.com/users/slim.ouertani

http://ouertani.github.io

http://www.jroller.com/ouertani http://twitter.com/ouertani

#### **INTERVIEW**

Paremus, SCA with OSGI, David Savage

http://www.prosyst.com/

07.02.2009

http://goo.gl/H5yJzY

## **MAGAZINE**

From Microservices to SOA - 20.07.2015 Service Technology Magazine - Issue XCI http://servicetechmag.com/I91/0715-1

## **STAMPLE**

https://stample.co Scala, Akka, Play ElasticSearch, MongoDb, Amazon S3, GreenCloud

#### **OPEN SOURCE**

https://github.com/ouertani http://www.reactive-streams.org

## Arcitura Authorized Training Partner

http://www.arcitura.com/ Big Data Science, Cloud & SOA

## **Publications**

Pour le fun: for-comprehension à la sauce Java 8	23.07.2015
Vrais ou Faux Jumeaux ?	25.11.2014
Curryfication Java: methods & fonctions	29.07.2014
Des Lenses en Java ?	30.06.2014
Barboter dans le compilateur Java	02.06.2014
Mon Trampoline avec Java 8	18.04.2014
Démystifier les iteratees avec Java	01.11.2013
Le Trio : Akka, Spring et Scala	16.10.2013
Rest with Scala and Vert.x	18.02.2013
Fun with Scala and Vert.x	11.02.2013

Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of publications since 2008.

## News

Publication de la Nouvelle Spécification d'ArchiMate 3.0	22.06.2016
Java EE et les Anges Gardiens	11.05.2016
Microservice antipatterns à Qcon London 2016	14.04.2016
MongoDB: la magie des Reactive-Streams avec les Capped Collections	21.05.2015
Publication de l'API Reactive Streams 1.0	07.05.2015
Docker, le dernier clou dans le cercueil des serveurs d'applications Java?	19.03.2015

## Languages

English, Arabic, French

Written & Spoken